foreign
so it's major munich 125. and
and
the reason we selected this particular
one it came up in the past and uh it's a
is a usual description of the gradual
training that the buddha would give
that the buddha would give
and um whereby when uh when a person has
become skilled
in abandoning hindrances
then there would be um
commonly the the
the the
description will continue by describing
the first jhana second jana third gen
and so on
and in this manjim 125 that that part is
different so instead of jhana
the buddha describes
[Music] the four foundations of mindfulness
the four foundations of mindfulness
there there in place of jhana
so i'll read out a bit having abandoned
these five hindrances imperfections of
mind of awareness they awaken the
discernment he remains mindful of the body within
he remains mindful of the body within
the body ardent alert and mindful
subduing greed and distress
joys and grieves griefs in regard to the
world he remains mindful of
feeling within feeling
mind within mind
and dharmas within dhammas ardent alert
and mindful subjecting greed and
distress in regard to the world um um
so
yes so the the
the common
standard description of satyabatana
body within the body
feelings within feelings mind within
mind and thoughts within thoughts
so the main
the main
the main point there it's as we said in
in the past talks is that um well in
order to be done rightly
it needs to be done for the right
reasons which means one needs to have a
right view in order to
to understand what body within body
actually is correctly how to see that
um so uh
the whole the whole the reason why these
satipatanos are the reference points
it's because generally
generally
um day-to-day experience is rooted
in um the sense of i am so they that
that's what i meant in the past when i
kept saying
uh like a
centralized and um where whereby you put
your sense of self first
now that's not something uh it's on the
level of choice so it's not done as a
matter of choice you don't choose to put
yourself first but by simply not having
the right view by um you know acting out
of desires uh irritations resistances
pressures and so on
all of those acts put your assumed
center self first
everything else is second so it's a
subtle thing it's easy to understand on
that like a coarser level but actually
the principle it's it's very subtle to
the point of the subtlest conceits are
these little perversions of what comes
first what you put first
so so in this sense
most common experience would be on the
level of um
well things are for me things are
happening to me uh pleasures are for me
pains are against me either way it's me
who is that center so even when people
practice to try to practice their sense
of mindfulness they do that through that
sense of me and through that sense of i
am
so the reason why satipatthanas
are the direct way as the buddha said
they would result in the complete
purification of beings of the mind of
the of the classes and everything that's
unwholesome is because you get to undo that wrong
is because you get to undo that wrong
order in this adipatanas so it's not
body for me body away from me
body's mind all these other things it's
basically you see body within the body
so there is no room for that sense of i
am to take over and become the center of
that experience and as i say it's the
right view for that is necessary because
if somebody is still not free from the
fetter of atavada
that assume the external sense of self
assume the external sense of self
external independent of this experience
as a whole
you couldn't possibly conceive but it's
meant by body within body i mean you can
have an idea of it but
so the whole the whole point of it is
somebody who has seen
uh the sense of self as within the
experience as a whole in the broadest
terms so somebody who is free from matavada
so somebody who is free from matavada
then all they need to do is use these
one of these
uh
for the reference points
that would then keep sustaining that
right order of putting that sense of i
am and conceit that's still there to
some extent just putting it second and
that's how it fades so it fades by not
being maintained in that gratuitously um
maintained in that gratuitously um
sort of um
elevated position of
of oh this is the center of the
experience and this this this person is
well the sense of i am is in charge and
so on and it's it's like the uh and
things revolve around it
so seeing whichever way you look you see
body within the body oh there is such an
such feeling present
not for me not in me not against me you
just feeling within that feeling
so either way wherever you look you look
at the right order puts one of these
four reference uh points uh puts them
first then sense of self of course for
somebody who is not fully enlightened
other hand
will still linger there
but your point is not to
intentionally try to get rid of the
attentive self the point is to sustain
the right order that prevents that sense
of self from taking over and assuming
that central position again so that's
why if the satipattan is done sustained
as reference point regardless of what
experience you're going through the
right order is sustained uh regardless
of what experience you're going through
so in other words you are purifying
yourself from the perversion of your own
conceit so that's what he's meant or he
so that's what he's meant or he
contemplates body in the body how well
by contemplating repulsiveness of the
body um subject to illness and so on so
all these things that basically that
would be freeing your mind from passion
in regard to body
is on the level of seeing body correctly
is not mine uh body is that which the my
sense of self depends upon not other way
around so seeing body in the body body
within the body whichever we want to say
so
that's what the first paragraph
describes um
having abandoned the five hindrances
he remains mindful so you have to have
uh
surmounted the the five hindrances so
sensual desire ill will sloth and toppo
uh doubt restlessness and worry and
doubt so these these are not
um these are not small things and they
would require quite a degree of wisdom
and that sort of uh right type of
endurance of not acting out of those
things until the mind has
seen beyond them until has ma until the
mind has learned how to operate under
them that's that's that's the point so
once the mind gets used to that those
hindrances do not exercise
as much power
over the mind and then he remains seeing
first as first body in the body
or feeling in the feeling
mind in the mind and none of that
is is taken up in that centralized sense
so that's the important bit here and
that's why exactly would lead to jhana
so this is not an accidental sort of
mix mix up to say like that
so then the buddha gives a simile
justice when the elephant plants a large
post in the ground and binds the
wilderness elephant to it by the neck in
order to break it of its wilderness
habits its wilderness memories resolves
distraction fatigue and fever over
leaving the wilderness to make a delight
in the town and teach it habits
congenial to human beings
so in the same way these four
foundations of mindfulness are bindings
for the
[Music] mindfulness of the disciple of the noble
mindfulness of the disciple of the noble
one and break him off his household
habits household memories and resolves
his distraction fatigue and fever over
leaving the household life for the
combination of the right method and the
realization so for the combination of
the right method for the combination of
the right view
which means you need to have head right
view in order for it to be brought to
combination um and uh
um and uh
in the same way these four foundations
are are bindings for the for the
mindfulness so these four
reference point
sustain the correct type of
recollectedness as we say
of
that non-perverted order so
and again i'm repeating this because
people might end up expecting okay so if
i'm rightly mindful there is no sense of
i am there is there is still conceit
there are still pressures there are
still desires but if instead you're
trying to
if instead of trying to engage with them
directly to i'll deal with this and then
i'll do this and then i'll keep saying
to myself
and removing the sense of self
uh
you instead actually invest your effort
in sustaining
the the reference point of body within
the body feeling within the feeling mind
within the mind thoughts within the
thoughts you are dealing with the
conceit you are uprooting it that's the
point so
by protecting the right order the
conceit is is being extinguished
eventually and that's what a noble
disciple would know which is why again
if what the buddha said if the inside
patana said if if he practices
like you know for seven days or what
seven months or seven years doesn't
matter the outcome of it will have to happen in
the outcome of it will have to happen in
other words the purification cannot not
happen because it's it's it's the only
thing that correctly established order
will result in
which is you know incidentally complete
freedom from suffering and enlightenment
so having abandoned the five hindrances
he um
he binds
um his mindfulness
correctly and these and that's what i'm
saying the conceit is still there the
pressures are still there that's exactly
what it's meant by the simile so the the
elephant's memories of the wilderness
and fatigue and distraction are still
there but the the tamer is not trying to count
but the the tamer is not trying to count
the elephant whenever elephant is sort
of acting out of its memories or desires
or pressures no he just binds him to
something that's seen as as thing that
can sustain that right order he binds
him to a post
of body in the body mind and mind and so
on
because that will calm all these wild
tendencies in it so it's the same for
the for the monk who trains or a person
who trains he finds
his wild mind his mind of conceit that
still tries to pressure him into
perverting the order through greed
aversion delusion
he binds it into this this um
right order and by doing so endures
these pulls and because he know he has
enough wisdom to see that to enduring
these polls having been bound in the
right order
these pressures and and wild tendencies
and household memories will fade away
so in other words he doesn't try to
manage them he has established the right
order that is resulting in direct
uprooting eventually sure not overnight
well for somebody maybe even overnight
as it would have said
um so
to target the trains in further come on
remain contemplating body within the
body feeling within the feeling so remain
feeling within the feeling so remain
a referenced in the right order remain
seeing the body
uh in that
decentralized sense as a thing that
endures there
because of which you have all these
precious pools and sense of i am because
of which you keep thinking you are the
center because of which your conceit keep
because of which your conceit keep
taking oh these are for me you see all
of that as second to the body so
whichever way you approach your
experience all you're gonna see is body
within this body or this body within the
body or feeling
within the enduring feeling
there's a feeling within me feeling for
me feeling away from me feeling against
me past feeling fear doesn't matter
feeling is there
within the feeling all the pressures all
the conceits all the
the the self-centered kind of notions
are peripherally enduring but you are
not abandoning the gateway of the right
order so
so
remain contemplating body in the body
and the other other references and do
not think any thoughts connected with
the sense desire
so that's always that that that thing
that we keep mentioning like sense uh
sensuality and since there has to be um
has to be overcome has to be understood
it won't disappear on its own so it has
to be overcome sorry through
understanding through not thinking the thoughts that
through not thinking the thoughts that
implied perversion of the order that
imply um putting beautiful first ugly second
um putting beautiful first ugly second
and so on
um they won't just disappear on account
of
you know
experiencing peaceful pleasure of of
focusing practices and something like
that no they they exp they disappear
when gratification danger and escape is
understood in regard to them
they still might be harassing the mind
that is rightly referenced but the point
is then to sustain that right reference
uh and then not give in to these
harassing thoughts they would want to
prevail and get you hooked on to
thinking uh well basically what um thinking that
uh well basically what um thinking that
uh ugly is beautiful and the desire is
that that comes first and the
satisfaction is there in the world
through the sense objects
so
do not think any thoughts of connect
connective desire so with stilling of
thinking and pondering he would then
enter in and remain
or he would remain having entered in the
second genre joy pleasure born of
composure unification of um of the mind
free from thinking and pondering
internal assurance internal confidence
so with fading of the joy he remains
equanimous mindful alert experiencing
pleasure with the body so then the
the this part of the suture then
concludes by by
[Music]
by saying having uh remain established
in the right order of seeing body within
the body
but do not think any thoughts connected
with centrality and uh not not thinking
any thoughts
doesn't mean like you prevent the
thoughts from arising
means not welcoming delighting accepting
any thoughts that are trying to pressure
you um
um
on account of or pressure you through
sensuality when you're correctly
referenced in seeing body within the
body any thoughts that are trying to
pressure you thoughts connected with
pleasures displeasures and so on you
don't accept them you don't welcome so
you don't think them so they will still
be buzzing around and trying to to
pervert the order as i said before but
purification and refinement of the
principle of mindfulness then results in
jhana as the buddha describes when you
start basically
even noticing those little pressures of
the little thoughts and not accepting
them and welcoming them so the god uh
the the gateway uh is is becomes
protected even in regard to those those
subtler subtle pressures that uh the
mind is otherwise kind of you know
accepting or noticing acting out and so
on not accepting not seeing uh not
accepting not putting first not
centralizing your experience around
those pressures
will then result in complete stilling
internally of thinking and
pondering and then
stealing of the of the
that rapture that's experienced in the body
rapture that's experienced in the body
and so on so it's important to um to
just repeat
that the point is to
sustain the right order
in face
of pressures that's pretty much
principle of the entire city patana but
in this sutta the buddha shows how that
principle
taken to its fulfillment
whereby uh
uh
thoughts of sensuality thoughts
connected in regard the body and the
pleasures of the body and the joys of
the body and the disability of the body
those thoughts are seen
through the right order of body within
the body so thoughts connected to the
with the body thoughts concerned about
the body are now seen
as uh bodily so to speak through the
right order of seeing body within the
body so when when somebody is
established in the mindfulness of the body
in the mindfulness of the body
uh
thoughts connected to the body thoughts
about sensuality could be still taken to
some extent as mine as the center of
experience in regard to this body
but the point is no by not taking them
by not delighting them by not welcoming
but not thinking them intentionally they
will be left there
sort of coming and going peripherally
enduring trying to pressure you trying
to assail you trying to pervert that
order through making you take them up if you
through making you take them up if you
don't take them up you just see body
within the body and everything else
even the subtlest
most pressing thoughts are seen now as
second as everything else
because if you start seeing them as
first means they have become centralized
again your conceit has perverted the
order so that's the practice of
purification i'm perverting and then
sustaining that
even to these subtle degrees doesn't
matter how personal those thoughts might
be
how subtle
um how fleeting they're all seen they
all remain second they all remain not
taken up not placed in this
self-centered uh sense of
experience yeah then
then this then the sutta continues on
just with standard description of if one
has developed his mind in this
in this manner to its fulfillment then
all the the the triple knowledges will
come and they're destroyed of the the
taints and and everything else so what
should be taken from this
is that um
[Music] one is the right view because without a
one is the right view because without a
right view one will not know what the
right endurance is
because one's endurance and everything
else one does will be still rooted
without a right view would still be
rooted in craving in trying to get rid
of discomfort you know what level you
have to endure the things for the
craving to cease
uh and by not knowing what level that is
you are acting out of craving and you're
feeding it
so once the person has drive you knows
what the um
and has been practicing the gradual
training because this this whole
description by the way you cannot just
take it and start doing it now this is
just towards the end of the of the
gradual training the gradual training
that starts with virtue
seeing the danger in the slightest fall
guarding of the center doors bought
fullness um moderation eating watchfulness
um moderation eating watchfulness
seclusion
and then the
all that basis that has been built up
well if somebody does this gradual
training rightly it will be highly
unlikely they won't have a right view by then by
they won't have a right view by then by
this by this time so to speak because if
one has taken the virtue rightly
uh is moderate is what full of his
intentions uh or behind his actions and
use the pressure
if acting out would uh imply that it
would reveal that it's rooted in great
diversion delusion
uh that's that's already sufficient uh
self transparency to start uh
basically recognizing
recognizing
that sense of self can actually come
second i mean you can say that yourself
you can imagine that you are not in
control uh but fundamentally as the buddha said
uh but fundamentally as the buddha said
without that right view a putujina would
be seeing self with self
would be seeing
uh self with not self would be seeing
not self with self but he can't see not
self with not self he can't see body in
the body he can't see body with the body
let's say like that he can't see feeling
with the feeling there has to be him
involved in seeing it or referring to it
so
having uh abandoned atavada having
abandoned that gertruder's
assumption of the sense of self existing
outside of this experience as a whole as
an independent owner master of it
you can actually see body within the
body or body with the body
or body with the body
feeling in the feeling because
sense of self is redundant that
self-centered seer the noah or whatever else people
seer the noah or whatever else people
call it it's completely redundant and
it's a symptom of the problem problem of
gratuitously perverting order
which with the perversion being
with the perversion being
kind of unknowingly
maintained and sustained through acting
under desire greed and aversion
and delusion sorry and ignoring a
neutral feeling and seeking distraction
from it
so
if that has been subdued through the
gradual training the reference point of
body within the body body just there or
sati patana also says
[Music] will make that
will make that
sense of self that's
self-centered assumption that the self has to be in
assumption that the self has to be in
the center that it is for me i am and so
on
will make that scene as as utterly
redundant and not necessary and now you
just have to keep sustaining that
knowledge and that recognition and not
carelessly give into the old habit of
putting yourself first putting a sense
of self first through desires ill will
and distraction
so seeing body in the body in other way
or feeling in the feeling that it means
exactly that being able that would not
self see not self
uh with
that which is clearly not mine
i see not mine in other words nothing
can be mined because this is the basis
of experience this is that reference
point so even all this pressure that i
might still be experiencing a kind of
traces of conceit that are around to
make me take things as mine to make the
me sort of accept welcome delight and
put it first i see even that as
something that cannot be taken as mine
and that can only be seen through a
rightly established order to the right
reference because if you think you're
seeing that directly like oh this cannot
be mine well that experience is yours
that experience has been taken as mine
that's why i said in the beginning it's
not a matter of choice you can't just
intentionally choose to not take
anything is mine
because that ex that intentional
experience is taken as yours
but if you see
that regardless of the extent of of
sense of i am regardless of the extent
of the ownership
assumptions in mind and
self-centeredness all of that
all of that
is within the enduring body here and now
is within the enduring feeling here and
now it's indeed within the enduring
state of mind here and now or within the
enduring uh thoughts most more specific
the context of your thoughts here and
now you realize okay so doesn't matter
you realize okay so doesn't matter
how far it goes how pressuring it is
it always is the second it cannot become
the first
the clearer the firmer the knowledge of
that is
the um
the possibility of perverting that order
ever again fades more and more and
that's exactly pretty much what it's
meant by purification of the mind pure
purification of of um
of things
that are unwholesome purification of our
servers or the taints and all the
different translations of it
means basically removal of the
possibility of perverting the order ever
again because if the order cannot be
perverted ever again nothing that used
to exist on a kind of perverted order
can manifest ever again desire anger
your will
sensuality conceit appropriation
ownership distraction delusion of egypt gone
distraction delusion of egypt gone
because the basis of it it's removed
through correct contemplation of body in
the body mind in the mind feeling the
feeling or
thoughts in the thoughts and that's
about it